<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The povver of kings discussed: or, An examen of the fundamentall constitution of the free-borne people of England: in answer to severall tenents of M. David Jenkins. By Will: Ball of Barkham, Esq;</title>
            <author>Ball, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E540_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205769</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865050</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865050</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164907</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77919)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164907)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E540[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The povver of kings discussed: or, An examen of the fundamentall constitution of the free-borne people of England: in answer to severall tenents of M. David Jenkins. By Will: Ball of Barkham, Esq;</title>
                  <author>Ball, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Harris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Jan. 30. 1648"; the "9" in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jenkins, David, 1582-1663.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Constitutional history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164907:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE POWER OF KINGS <hi>DISC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SSED:</hi> OR, An Examen of the Fundamentall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Free-borne People of <hi>ENGLAND:</hi> In Anſwer to ſeverall Tenents of M. <hi>David Jenkins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Will: Ball</hi> of <hi>Barkham,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sat Patriae Priamo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> datum</hi>—</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for JOHN HARRIS, 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:164907:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:164907:2"/>
            <head>THE POVVER OF <hi>KINGS</hi> DISCUSSED, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Free-borne people of <hi>England</hi> live or ought to live by or under a <hi>Law of common conſent,</hi> the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Ruler or higheſt Magiſtrate whereof is the KING, whoſe Oath is to conſerve and maintaine <hi>juſtas leges &amp; conſuetudines quas vulgus elegerit, &amp;c.</hi> the juſt Lawes and Cuſtomes which the Common People <hi>ſhall chooſe,</hi> (as many doe expound it.) Others will have the Verbe <hi>elegerit</hi> to ſignifie <hi>hath choſen,</hi> according to the French <hi>Aur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n choiſy:</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> alledgeth this reaſon for it,
<note place="margin">Jenk. Reſp. ad Prin.</note> 
               <hi>Cuſtomes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not referre to future time, and both are coupled together, Lawes and cuſtomes;</hi> ſo that <hi>Elegerit</hi> muſt be taken in the Preterperfect Tenſe: But by the favour of Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> albeit Cuſtomes are not properly alterable as are Lawes, and though Lawes and Cuſtomes are coupled together, yea alterable Lawes are nominated and placed before Cuſtomes; yet may the verbe <hi>Elegerit</hi> be taken in the future Tenſe; for the Reaſon why <hi>Lawes</hi> are inſerted in the Kings Oath, or propounded to the King in his Oath before <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes,</hi> is, firſt, becauſe <hi>Lawes</hi> are more worthy and noble then Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, for that Lawes are Rules or Regulations of the whole or entire People, but Cuſtomes are Rules onely of ſome or of a part of the People, and that in ſome things onely.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Lawes</hi> are more ancient, to ſpeake generally, then <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> for it's very probable that the Saxons comming out of <hi>Germany</hi> into <hi>Britaine</hi> brought the <hi>Common Law</hi> with them, as a Rule agreeable to the Law of Nature and Reaſon, which they had learned or had delivered unto them from their fathers; yet <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> they could not bring with them, for <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> have Relation to Place as well as to Perſons, but neither the Saxons, nor any other
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:164907:3"/>People could have Relation to a Land or Country before they poſſeſſed it: ſo that the coupling of <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> together, or Nominating or Placing <hi>Lawes</hi> before Cuſtomes in the Kings Oath, is no amiable Reaſon, From whence a direct conſequence may be deduced, that the Verbe <hi>Elegerit</hi> muſt or ought to be taken in the Preterperfect Tenſe, or that it may not be taken in the Future-Tenſe, and conſequently that the King may not be ſtrictly tyed and obliged <hi>in foro conſcientiae,</hi> to conſerve and maintaine ſuch juſt Lawes as the Common-People ſhall at any time make choiſe of: but admitting the Verbe <hi>Elegerit</hi> to be taken and expounded in the Preterperfect Tenſe, albeit there be difference in Grammar, yet is there no great difference in <hi>Logick</hi> or Reaſon; for the King taking his Oath <hi>to maintaine the juſt Lawes and Cuſtome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which the People or Common-People have choſen, taketh his Oath by an Implicite or Tacite condition to conſerve and maintaine the juſt Lawes which the People ſhall chuſe;</hi> for at the firſt making of that Oath, and at our Kings their taking of it ever ſince, the Common-people had then choſen, and have ever ſince <hi>conſerved</hi> ſuch choiſe, that not only there ſhould be no Lawes <hi>de futuro,</hi> for the time to come, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their <hi>Conſent,</hi> but alſo that upon their Requeſt or Petition our Kings ſhould Redreſſe ſuch Agrievances as they ſhould complaine of, and likewiſe propagate ſuch juſt Lawes as they ſhould propound conducing to their generall good or welfare: and that was the Reaſon why heretofore it was inſerted in many Statutes, <hi>Be it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enacted by the Kings Majeſty, with Aſſent of the Lords, &amp;c. and at the Requeſt of the Commons,</hi> &amp;c. wherein two things are to be noted, firſt, that the Commons did Requeſt, not command or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force our Kings to paſſe ſuch Acts; ſecondly, that our Kings did upon ſuch Requeſts uſually paſſe them. And albeit the King have a Negative voice, or rather a voice for adviſe, or to adviſe, as the words <hi>Le Roy ſ'aviſera</hi> import, yet I conceive that he is ſtrictly tyed <hi>in Foro conſcientiae</hi> according to his Oath, and the end of his Government (which is the good of the People) to paſſe ſuch Acts for Civill Government as the Commons ſhall Requeſt him to paſſe.
<note place="margin">Jenk. Reſp. ad Prin.</note> But Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> and others make a <hi>Quaere</hi> and aske, <hi>who ſhall be Judges?</hi> whether ſuch Lawes as the Commons ſhall Requeſt be juſt or no, the King is tyed or obliged by Oath only to propagate and maintaine the juſt Lawes which the Common-People chuſe or Requeſt. In Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> his opinion, the judges and the Maſters of Chancery, with the Lords or Peers aſſiſting the King ought to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:164907:3"/>be judges of the Common-People, or of their Repreſentatives, or Truſtees their Requeſts, rather then two, or three, or a few Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners, who ſometimes are not learned in the Lawes of the Land. To this Quaere, and the Allegations, I anſwer, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons <hi>Primario,</hi> or in the firſt Place are, and ought to be <hi>the judges,</hi> even as Cuſtomary Tenants are, and ought to be their owne Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences; <hi>although one man ought not to be judge in his owne Caſe, yet all in a Kingdome, or Common-wealth, can have no judges of their Common Intereſt but themſelves, or ſome amongſt themſelves, at leaſtwiſe no Competent judges:</hi> and where the <hi>Common Intereſt</hi> is controverted, there they, who have the greateſt <hi>Intereſts,</hi> or whom it moſt concernes, ought to be judges <hi>Primario</hi> or in the firſt place; and ſurely the Common People in generall have the greateſt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in their <hi>Common Intereſt,</hi> and the Lawes of the Land moſt concerne them, wherefore they, or their Repreſentatives, or Truſtees, ought to be judges <hi>Primario,</hi> or in the firſt place. And as touching that, many in the Houſe of Commons are not ſomtimes learned in the Lawes, nor have any great knowledge in State affaires; it may be ſo; and it may be wiſhed, that none but ſuch as have ſound judgments, might ſit in that Honourable Houſe, and I beleeve that the words <hi>habiles homines,</hi> in the writ of Burgeſſes intend ſuch men, and not men of great Eſtates, who are ſometimes men of meane underſtandings, and yet by feaſting (I will not ſay Bribing) or by flattering, or by an over-awing Power, attaine to be Parliament men; howſoever, for as much as ſuch men being choſen, are capable to conſult and adviſe with others wiſer then themſelves, and are in matters of great Concernment, guided by the Diſcretion of others, their votes going along with the votes of others, they may be accompted competent judges, of what may be beneficiall, or prejudiciall, to the Common-wealth. Howſoever I doe not exclude the Lords, or the Houſe of Peeres from being judges <hi>ſecundario</hi> of ſuch matters, as generally concerne the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: for although Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> conceive them not to be <hi>Vulgus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jenk Reſp. ad Prin.</note> truly I conceive the Lords in England to be but <hi>vulgus ſuperlatum,</hi> even as Biſhops are but <hi>clerici Prelati,</hi> and Aldermen but <hi>cives elati;</hi> in England the Nobles have no diſtinct or different Lawes, as in Germany, Poland, and ſome other countries; theſe here inherit by the Common Law, or Lawes Common to others; they alſo contract Bargaine and ſale by the ſame Lawes, and are ſubject to the ſame Lawes; ſome Priveledges they have which make ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164907:4"/>a Titulary, or circumſtantiall, then an Eſſentiall or ſpecificall difference, between them and the inferiour Common-People. But it may be ſome will ſay, why ſhould not the Lords being dignified, or Noble, be Judges <hi>Primariò,</hi> or in the firſt place, rather then the Commons? I anſwer, that the Lords are not intruſted by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as are the Commons, and therefore in matters of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall concernment, the Commons ought to precede them; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>de ſe &amp; ſuis</hi> in things that meerely concerne the Lords, as alſo concerning matters of Fact,
<note n="*" place="margin">And for this cauſo, as alſo to adviſe the King, are the Iudges, &amp; Maſters of Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry called to the Houſe of Peeres. <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his [<hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall.</hi> &amp;c.]</note> or controverſie which ſhall happen by writs of <hi>Error,</hi> or otherwiſe to come into that moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe, therein the Lords <hi>De Jure</hi> precede the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. But Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> will have the Houſe of Peeres to be Judges of the Lawes, rather then the Houſe of Commons, becauſe the King by his writ ſaith, <hi>that he will conſult and treat with the Peeres, and Prelates of the Kingdome, for, and touching the great Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Common-wealth</hi> (for the King never ſits in the Houſe of Commons) the Peeres doe <hi>conſulere</hi> and conſequently (as ſaith Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi>) judge of the concernments of the Common-wealth, the Commons doe but <hi>Facere et conſentire,</hi> according to ſuch Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or judgment; which Power <hi>ad faciendum &amp; conſentiendum</hi> Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſaith the King gives them by his writ; &amp; to ſtrengthen his Opinion he quoteth a great Lawyer: But by the favour of Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and ſuch as adhere to his opinion, albeit the King ſay in his writ, that he will conſult and treate with the Prelates and Peeres, touching the great concernments of the Common-wealth, for that they are properly his Aſſiſtants, he ſitting with them, doth he therefore ſay that he will not treate with the Commons? nay, doth not the King treate with the Commons, by Meſſengers, when he deſireth Aides and Subſidies, and have not the Commons a Negative voice therein? can the King and the Peeres make an Act of Law without the Commons? are the Commons tyed or obliged neceſſarily <hi>to doe and conſent</hi> to what the King and the Lords ſhall determine, as Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſeemes to intimate? ſurely no, our Lawes and cuſtomes ſpeake them abſolutely free in theſe things. And whereas Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſaith that the King by his writ gives Power to the Commons, <hi>ad faciendum &amp; conſentiendum,</hi> therein he is greatly miſtaken; the King by his writ onely appoints the place and time, and inſtances the words, <hi>ad faciendum &amp; conſentiendum, to ſhew the cauſe or End of their Convention or aſſembling together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> but the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple give them their Power, who elect or nominate them, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:164907:4"/>alſo tranſact their Power unto them, by their Parole at their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, and by their Indentures wherein they inſert the words, <hi>ad faciendum &amp; conſentiendum,</hi> as from themſelves to the Part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, whom in the ſaid Indentures they Nominate and intruſt: and indeed, were the Power of the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, derived to them by the Kings writ, ſuch Indentures were needleſſe and frivolous, the Sheriffs might only make their Return, <hi>ſe feciſſe Electionem ſecundum Breve receptum,</hi> and ſuch like. Moreover, it is againſt Reaſon that a People ſhall have Power to nominate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt ſome about their Affaires, and ſhall, for that end, allow them wages, (as doe the Counties, Cities, and Townes Corporate, to the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes) and yet that ſuch Truſtees or Stewards ſhould derive no Power from the People their Truſtors, neither as their Judges <hi>Delegate,</hi> nor <hi>Allegate;</hi> that is to ſay, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Judges for them according to Law, nor as Judges for them according to Reaſon and Conſcience. But M. <hi>Jenkins</hi> conceiveth, the Houſe of Commons to be no fit Judges of Lawes, or Acts for the Peoples good, becauſe they are not called <hi>ad conſiliandum,</hi> but the Houſe of Peeres. And furthermore,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his <hi>[Lex Terrae.]</hi> and his <hi>[Cordiall.]</hi>
               </note> that the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons are no Court, at leaſtwiſe no Court of Record, nor can give an Oath, or examine upon Oath; <hi>And that Houſe which cannot doe the leſſe, cannot doe the greater.</hi> By M. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and other his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents favour, is it not of greater moment and concernment to be called <hi>ad faciendum &amp; conſentiendum,</hi> then <hi>ad conſiliandum,</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium dandum?</hi> He, or they, who are called to Councell, are called only to adviſe with; but he, or they, who are called <hi>ad faciendum &amp; conſentiendum,</hi> are called to Act with, or to be Co-enactors.</p>
            <p>Therefore the King, by his Writ, invites the People <hi>to doe and conſent,</hi> (by their Repreſentatives) <hi>touching ſuch difficult and urgent affaires as concerne Himſelf, the State, and defence of the Kingdome of</hi> England, <hi>and Church of</hi> England, <hi>of which He intends to Conſult with His Peeres:</hi> And great Reaſon it is that the Common-wealth ſhould, at the leaſt, have free Power in her ſelf to acknowledge her own, <hi>Finalem Concordantiam,</hi> her own, <hi>Facere &amp; conſentire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> albeit ſhe were in nature of <hi>Femine Covert Baron</hi> (as M. <hi>Jenkins</hi> would have her) the King being <hi>ſponſus Regni,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his [<hi>Lex Ter.</hi> p, 41.]</note> qui per annulum is eſpouſed to his Realme at His Coronation:</hi> And certainly the King conceives ſuch Power inherent in the Common-wealth, when He declares in His Writ, <hi>Ita quod pro defectu Poteſtatis hujuſmodi, ſeu propter impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidam Electionem Militum Civium, &amp; Burgenſium, &amp;c.</hi> Moreover, I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164907:5"/>could tell M. <hi>Jenkins</hi> that Common-wealth hath greater Power<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The KING receives the Ring at His Coronation, as doth <hi>Femme Covert Baron,</hi> and conſequently the Common-wealth rather eſpouſes the King, then the King the Common-wealth: So that the Common-wealth is <hi>Regina ſui ipſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> the King, <hi>Rex Rege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> as was <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Spain</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> albeit <hi>modo difference,</hi> for he was King meerly of Courteſie, but our Kings are Kings by Deſcent: And whereas M. <hi>Jenkins</hi> doth in ſeverall places except againſt the Power of the Houſe of Commons, affirming that they are not fit to be <hi>Judges of the Lawes of the Land,</hi> for that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not puniſh Felony, or Treaſon, nor give an Oath, nor are a Court of Record, &amp;c. It maketh no matter whether they can doe theſe things, or whether they are a Court of Record or no, in relation of their being <hi>Judges of the Lawes of the Land,</hi> ſo farre forth as they are to judge of them; for the Commons are not called and choſen chiefly to judge of matters <hi>de facto,</hi> according to the Lawes <hi>in Being,</hi> (for that the Courts of Juſtice may determine of) but to judge of the Lawes themſelves,
<note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>De Facto &amp; de Fieri,</hi> whether they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient or inconvenient, fit to be continued, or repealed; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new Lawes ought to be made for the good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth or no; and theſe things they may doe as <hi>Judges Allegate,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpeeres</hi> for the People, although the Houſe of Commons were no Court of Record. Moreover, I conceive that he, or they, who covenant with others to doe any Act, or Acts, which ſhall be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably adviſed, or deviſed by the Covenantees, or their Councell, or the like, doth make ſuch Covenantees their Councell, or Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trators, Judges <hi>Primario,</hi> or in the firſt place of ſuch Act or Acts, and ſuch Covenantors make themſelves, or become <hi>Paſſive to the end, and Active to the meanes of ſuch Covenant,</hi> that is to ſay, they are to doe, or Act what the Covenantees will (with Reaſon) have them doe or Act, albeit the Acts which they do are their own Acts; even ſo that <hi>Potentate,</hi> who Covenanteth by Oath (for his Oath is <hi>Vice contractus vel compacti</hi>) to conſerve and maintain the Juſt Lawes and Cuſtomes which the People <hi>ſhall chuſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> or otherwiſe the Juſt Lawes and Cuſtomes which the People <hi>have choſen,</hi> (it being one of their Choſen Lawes, that their <hi>Potentates</hi> ſhall <hi>de futuro</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Requeſt, redreſſe their Agrievances, be it by repealing Acts inconvenient, or enacting ſome <hi>de Novo</hi>) ſuch Potentate doth ſurely make the People their Repreſentatives or Truſtees, Judges <hi>Pirmario,</hi> or in the firſt place of ſuch Act, and makes himſelf, or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:164907:5"/>becomes <hi>Paſſive to the end, and Active to the meanes of ſuch his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract by Oath;</hi> that is to ſay, He is to doe what the People will (with Juſtice and Reaſon) have him to doe or Act, albeit the Acts which he doth are his own Acts. But M. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſaith, that both Houſes have many times tendred unto our Kings, unjuſt and unreaſonable Bills, which it had been better for our Kings to have denied, or not have paſſed, then to have conſented to, and have paſſed; and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> inſtanceth touching Religion, Bills tendred to <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. and to Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> Bills tendred unto <hi>Richard</hi> the 3. and alſo to the aforeſaid <hi>Henry</hi> the 8.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his <hi>[Lex Terrae.]</hi>
               </note> concerning Civill Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c. I conceive M. <hi>Jenkins</hi> might have inſtanced enough, and to many ſuch Bills, but what of all this? Is there not <hi>Bonum Reale,</hi> and <hi>Bonum apparens, ſecundum tendentiam vellietatis,</hi> Reall Good, and ſeeming Good, which may be in it ſelf evill? and is there not <hi>verum Reale,</hi> and <hi>verum Formalt, ſecundum quod ad ſe fert Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus;</hi> a Reall Truth, or a true Reall Being, and an apprehended Truth, or a true apprehended Being, which may be no true Reall Being; even ſo there is <hi>juſtum Reale,</hi> and <hi>juſtum appaerens,</hi> or <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male,</hi> an Act, or Being Really juſt, and ſeemingly or formally Juſt, as it is apprehended by underſtanding, and embraced by the will, which may be in it ſelf unjuſt: wherefore, if the People (to whom the King is tyed by Oath) or their Repreſentatives or Truſtees, ſo long and ſo farre as they intruſt them, ſhall on behalfe of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple tender to the King, a Bill of Civill Government to them, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Juſt and Reaſonable; but to the King ſeeming unjuſt and unreaſonable, and it may be ſo in it ſelf, the King notwithſtanding, is by an Implicite Condition of his Oath, tyed or obliged to paſſe ſuch a Bill if it deprive not himſelfe, of his owne <hi>Juſt Rights,</hi> for <hi>Id juris eſt quod Nationis eſt,</hi> if a Nation or People, will induce themſelves into an inconvenience, conceiving it convenience, the King cannot help it; he may uſe the beſt meanes he can, by adviſe, Arguments, and the like, to prevent it; but if the People, and their Repreſentatives, wil perſevere in their Deſire or Requeſt, the KING (as aforeſaid) is obliged to paſſe it, The KING is the ſupreme Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or higheſt Magiſtrate for the People, or over the People <hi>ad agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> to put the Lawes in Execution; but the KING is not chiefe Judge of the Rules, or Lawes, by which the People will be Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; the People themſelves, and thoſe whom they intruſt ſo farre as they intruſt them, are, or ought to be Judges thereof <hi>Jure Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive:</hi> moreover, if a Covenantee will deſire, or require of a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantor
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:164907:6"/>an Act, (of which the Covenantee is Judge <hi>Primariò,</hi> or in the firſt Place) no way beneficiall, but rather detrimentall to him the Covenantee, the Covenantor is obliged to grant, or performe ſuch an Act tending to the end of his Covenant, not otherwiſe to endamage himſelfe; even ſo it is between the KING who is Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantor by Oath, and the People who are Covenantees concerning Lawes and Statutes touching Civil Government to be enacted, or repealed, and aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>But ſome it may be will ſay, ſuppoſe the Commons or both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament ſhould tender unto the KING a Bill, or Bills, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to His owne <hi>Juſt Rights,</hi> is he bound to paſſe ſuch? truly no! He may juſtly refuſe them, for the End of His Oath is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and maintain the <hi>Juſt Lawes</hi> which the People <hi>have choſen,</hi> or <hi>ſhall chuſe,</hi> for their Good; not the unjuſt Lawes which they ſhall chuſe to deſtroy or deprive Him of His <hi>Royall Right: Jus Regnandi</hi> is the <hi>Kings</hi> by diſcent, even as <hi>Jus Regni</hi> (to ſpeake properly) is the Peoples by birth-right, (no way excluding the <hi>King</hi> from any bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thereof) The People promiſe or Covenant by Oath to obey the <hi>King</hi> as their ſupreame Governour or higheſt Magiſtrate, and to maintaine Him, His Heires, and lawfull Succeſſours, in His, and their juſt Rights and Dignities; and as the <hi>Kings</hi> Oath tieth and obligeth Him to the People, certainly the Peoples Oath tieth and obligeth them to the <hi>King:</hi> although our <hi>King</hi> in <hi>England</hi> be not a <hi>Perſonall Monarch</hi> to make Lawes, and Governe at His pleaſure, as ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that the <hi>Great Turke,</hi> the <hi>King of Perſia,</hi> and ſuch like Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Princes do; (albeit, I conceive, that even thoſe Potentates are in ſome things limited) yet out <hi>King</hi> is a <hi>Legall Monarch</hi> to Reigne and Governe by Lawes made and conſented unto by the People; <hi>ſo that although the King have not an abſolute Power to make Lawes,
<note place="margin">☞</note> He hath an abſolute Power to adminiſter the Lawes;</hi> and I hope there are none that will thinke or attempt otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid, that the <hi>King</hi> is tied by an implicite Condition of His Oath (admitting the Verb <hi>Elegerit</hi> to be underſtood in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terperfect tenſe) to paſſe ſuch Bills concerning Civill Government as the Commons or both Houſes ſhall tender unto Him, (not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Himſelfe) and having ſaid, notwithſtanding, that the <hi>King</hi> hath a Negative Voice, or a Voice to adviſe, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not to paſſe ſuch Bills untill he have adviſed; ſome it may be will ſay, that there is a contradiction or oppoſition in theſe Aſſertions; but there is none, for even every Covenantor may be the courteſie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:164907:6"/>of the Law adviſe with Himſelfe and His owne Councell, as well as with the Councell of His Covenantee, before He make or doe Acts tending to the End of His Covenant, and great Reaſon it is, that the <hi>King</hi> ſhould have as great, or rather greater Freedome in that He is the ſupreme Ruler, or higheſt Magiſtrate of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; a freedome to adviſe, or to deny untill adviſe be taken doth not <hi>Nul nec in foro conſcientiae, nec in foro Juris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> the tie or obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Oath or Covenant ſo farre forth as ſuch Oath or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant tieth or obligeth.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, concerning the <hi>Kings</hi> Oath aforeſaid, although He be tied and obliged by vertue thereof to paſſe Bills touching Civill Government, (as aforeſaid) yet I conceive that He is not tied and obliged by vertue of His ſaid Oath, to paſſe Bills touching Religion, tendred unto Him by the Commons, or both Houſes of Parliament; for, at the making of that Oath, neither the Commons, nor their Repreſentatives, or Truſtees; nor the <hi>King,</hi> or His Lords, or Peers, had any thing to doe, or did meddle with matters touching Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to define, frame, or alter any thing therein; ſuch things were then altogether performed by Eccleſiaſticall Councels and Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; nor would the People, nor did they tie or oblige the <hi>King</hi> by Oath to doe that which (as then) they conceived He had no Power to doe: and the <hi>Kings,</hi> who have ſucceſſively taken that Oath ſince the firſt making thereof, have taken their Oathes according to the intent and meaning of that Oath when firſt compiled, and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; ſo that I doe not conceive the <hi>King</hi> to be obliged by vertue of His ſaid Oath to paſſe Bills touching Religion tendred unto Him by the Commons, or both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>But ſome (it may be) will ſay, that the <hi>King</hi> is tied otherwiſe <hi>Ex Officio,</hi> to paſſe ſuch Bills touching Religion, as the Commons, or both Houſes ſhall tender unto Him; it may be ſo, but if ſo, yet both the <hi>King,</hi> and both the Houſes, ought to be very cautelous and conſcientious how they make Acts touching Religion, in which they may erre themſelves, and by which they may enſnare and moleſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Conſciences: however, the Kirk-men having borrowed (I ſuppoſe) ſome infallible Night-caps from the Roman Biſhops, dreame exceedingly, that they interpret the holy Scriptures without errour of the leaſt <hi>Iota.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Principium Caput,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his <hi>[Lex Terrae.]</hi>
                  </note> &amp; finis Parlamenti;</hi> the <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Principium,</hi> I grant Him, for that the <hi>King</hi> by His Writ appoints the time, and place, of Parliamentary
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164907:7"/>Conventions, and that the <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Caput,</hi> I alſo grant it Him in that the <hi>King</hi> is the ſupreme Ruler, or higheſt Magiſtrate of the Common-wealth; but that the <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Finis,</hi> at leaſtwiſe, <hi>Finis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teger aut tetalis Parlamenti,</hi> I deny it; for <hi>Finis,</hi> or <hi>cauſa finaelis,</hi> is <hi>cauſa propter quod,</hi> the cauſe for which a thing is ordained; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, <hi>ſalus Populi,</hi> which is <hi>ſuprema Lex,</hi> the ſafety of the People, their generall good and welfare is the <hi>end;</hi> at leaſtwiſe, the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall end</hi> of Parliamentary Conventions: and Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſeemeth in his <hi>[Cordiall to the good People of London]</hi> to acknowledge as much, for whereas Maſter <hi>H. P.</hi> Barriſter of <hi>Lincolns Inne</hi> affirmeth, that <hi>the ſafety of the People is the ſupreame Law,</hi> (as indeed it is:) Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> replying to him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his <hi>[Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall.]</hi>
               </note> faith, <hi>Neither doe we ſweare, but His Majeſty and we will ſweare to the contrary, and have ſworne and have made good, and will by Gods grace make good our Oath to the World, that the KING is not above the Law, nor above the ſafety of His People, the Law and the ſafety of His People, are His ſafety, His Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and His ſtrength:</hi> theſe are Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> his words, whereby he acknowledgeth, That the ſafety of the People are the <hi>Kings</hi> ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, honour, and ſtrength; ſo that if the <hi>King</hi> be the <hi>end,</hi> or a <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall end</hi> of the Parliament, according to his Aſſertion, the Peoples ſafety muſt needs be the <hi>principall or ultimate end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſaith, <hi>That it cannot be ſaid the King doth wrong,</hi> and that it was declared by all the Judges, and Serjeants at Law, <hi>[Tempore.]</hi> The Reaſon is, (ſaith Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi>) <hi>Nothing can be done in this Common-wealth by the Kings Grant, or any other Act of His, as to the Perſons, Goods, Lands, Liberties of the Subjects, but must be according to the eſtabliſhed Lawes, which the Judges are ſworne to ebſerve and deliver between the King and His People, impartially to rich and poore, high and low; and therefore the Justices and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Juctice are to be queſtioned and puniſhed if the Lawes be vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and no Reflection to be made on the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> favour, if it be granted, that the <hi>King</hi> doth not wrong in miniſtring the Lawes, but that the Miniſters of the Lawes whom the <hi>King</hi> intruſteth doe the wrong, will it therefore follow, that <hi>it cannot be ſaid that the King doth the wrong,</hi> otherwiſe both in His naturall and politique capacity? ſurely no! The <hi>King</hi> may uſurp (and yet be a King <hi>de Facto</hi>) as did <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Robert</hi> being alive; and <hi>William</hi> the ſecond alſo, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Fathers Will; <hi>Stephen; Richard</hi> the firſt, and <hi>John</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (for <hi>Arthur</hi> Sonne of <hi>Geoffry</hi> Duke of <hi>Britaine,</hi> third Sonne
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:164907:7"/>of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond was right Heire to the Crowne, <hi>Richard</hi> being the fourth Sonne, and <hi>John</hi> the fift Sonne of the ſaid <hi>King Henry</hi>) <hi>Edward</hi> the third, while his Father lived (for though his Father were a diſſolute Prince, yet the Son ought not to have uſurped his Right; and albeit a People may (as did the petty Kings and People of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> the Jewes, Athenians, Romans, and divers other Nations) free themſelves from tyranny and ſlavery, yet they ought not Depoſe their <hi>King</hi> for vice) <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth that ſubtile Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>Richard</hi> the third that politique Tyrant.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> may break his faith and promiſe with his own People, and others, as did the <hi>Norman,</hi> and ſome of his Succeſſours very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, as if it had deſcended to them with the Crowne.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> may break his Oath, as did <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and ſome others.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> may, through his owne covetous and ambitious deſire, impoſe illegall Taxes upon the People, he may alſo engage himſelf and his People in unneceſſary Wars and Broiles, as <hi>Kings</hi> have done either; and if it be ſaid, that <hi>Kings</hi> are in ſuch things many times miſled by their Councels, and therefore they themſelves ought to be excuſed; I anſwer, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for, <hi>Kings</hi> ought not to be miſled by their Councels, <hi>Privatio Rectitudinis in debito eſſe Actus Peccatum eſt; Kings</hi> have the meanes not to be miſled in ſuch matters if they will make uſe of it; but many times <hi>Kings</hi> will be led by Cabinet Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, Creatures of their owne making, who depend upon them, and endeavour to humour and pleaſe their Princes for their owne Ends, and not to counſell them according to prudence and juſtice: and ſometimes <hi>Kings</hi> have done what liketh themſelves without counſell.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> may by an over-awing Power, or by a kind of mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, or high carriage, enforce, or cauſe the Repreſentatives of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> to doe, or agree to that, to which (if ſuch unjuſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct meanes were not uſed) they would not agree unto; as did <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, in obtaining the Lands of Abbies and Monaſteries; for admit the Abbies and Monaſteries deſerved to be diſſolved, yet for as much as their Lands were <hi>Terrae Regni non Regis,</hi> they ought to have been applied, and employed to the good of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> not of the <hi>King,</hi> there being then neither Law, Reaſon, not Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for it: but K. <hi>Henry</hi> partly by frownes, mutterings, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and partly by promiſing that he would with thoſe Lands maintaine an Army for the defence of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and eaſe the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:164907:8"/>People from other Taxes, and Payments, (which how well he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, all men know) obtained and got into his hands thoſe Lands by conſent of both the Houſes of Parliament: wherein how juſtly, or unjuſtly, both Houſes dealt, I will not diſpute it at this time.</p>
            <p>But to goe on,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his <hi>[Lex Terrae.]</hi>
               </note> M. <hi>Jenkins</hi> himſelf inſtanceth, that <hi>in King</hi> Johns <hi>time the Nobles and Commons of the Realme conceiving that the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cuſtomes and Rights were violated, &amp;c.</hi> Et paulo poſt, <hi>after the ſubjects had obtained their Rights and Liberties, which were no other then their Ancient Cuſtomes, &amp;c.</hi> by which two inſtances of his, He in ſome ſort acknowledgeth that the People were wronged <hi>in their Cuſtomes and Rights,</hi> from the time of the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt, to the Reigne of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. and who did the wrong? Surely the <hi>Norman</hi> and his Succeſſours, who ſeverally violated them, not ſuch Judges and Juſtices of the Lawes who then were, for they did but as they were commanded: To conclude, the <hi>King</hi> may in theſe and the like things, both according to his naturall and politique capacity, <hi>Peccare contra Deum, contra Proximum, &amp; ſeipſum,</hi> and if it be ſaid, notwithſtanding, He can doe no wrong, certainly that <hi>tenet</hi> if it be <hi>Ens Legis,</hi> it is ſcarce <hi>Ens rationis Ratiocinatae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>King</hi> can doe no wrong <hi>[in Curiâ,]</hi> nor the <hi>Pope</hi> erre <hi>[in Cathedrâ,]</hi> I take them to be Axioms much alike: for my part I pretend not to the knowledge of the Lawes, but honour the knowledge thereof: thus much I know, <hi>non jurari in verba magiſtri,</hi> I have heard ſay, that the greateſt Clerks are not ſometimes the wiſeſt men; and I muſt tell M. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and others, that ſometimes alſo the greateſt Lawyers are not the ſoundeſt School-men, for if they were, ſome of them would not have ſaid, and written, what they have: M. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his <hi>[Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall.]</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Law and Cuſtome of this Land, is, that a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath Power over my life, liberty, lands, and goods, and over every other ſubject, &amp;c. Pax cum pedibus,</hi> good Maſter <hi>Jenkins,</hi> not ſo faſt; what doth Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> meane by the word, <hi>Power?</hi> if he meane by the word, <hi>Power,</hi> that the Parliament hath power to protect the lives, liberties, &amp;c. of the People, I grant it him; or if he meane by the word, <hi>Power,</hi> that the Parliament hath power <hi>applicare in neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitatum Regni,</hi> the Proprieties of the People, I alſo grant it him; but if Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> meane by the word, <hi>Power,</hi> that the Parliament (including the <hi>King</hi>) hath an abſolute Power to diſpoſe of the Peoples Eſtates <hi>merè ad Placitum,</hi> I abſolutely deny it; and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this, I have formerly inſerted Reaſons in two Printed Books:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:164907:8"/>Moreover, the Parliament cannot <hi>Tradere Populum Angliae aliene Juri,</hi> deliver over the Free People of <hi>England</hi> to a foraine Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to Lawes impoſed by Forainers, or compoſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in relation to Forainers; nor can the Parliament by any Ordinance, or Act whatſoever, deprive the Free people of <hi>England</hi> of their innate Right of electing Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes for Parliament; in theſe things, and things of the nature of theſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fundamentall Rights and Lawes of the People, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament cannot, nor ought not any way to violate the People, or Nation; if they doe it, they doe not onely fall and faile from the Protection of the People, but they become <hi>Preditores &amp; Hoſtes Patriae:</hi> The <hi>King</hi> is to conſider that although he have his <hi>Jus Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi,</hi> his Crowne by diſcent, and holds <hi>à Deo ordinariâ per ſucceſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> God himſelf being the Efficient Cauſe primarily, yet he holds it <hi>in ordine ad Populum,</hi> in relation to the People, who tie him by Oath, &amp;c. in <hi>England, ſalus Populi,</hi> not <hi>Majeſtas Imperii,</hi> is the chief object and end of Government: The Repreſentatives or Truſtees of the People are alſo to conſider that they are <hi>creati in Ordine ad Populum,</hi> not <hi>Nati in Ordine ad ſe,</hi> as are the Venetian Senators; that they are intruſted by the People according to the Kings Writ, <hi>Pro quibuſdam arduis &amp; urgentibus Negotiis,</hi> not made unlimited or abſolute in all things; ſo that the King and both the Houſes of Parliament ought to endeavour for the generall good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
            <p>I am of Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> his Opinion in this, <hi>That the ſafety of the People is the ſafety of the King,</hi> and that the honour of the King is ſupported by the honour of the People, or Nation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILLIAM BALL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
